Register of the Aleksandr Nikolaevich Krupenskiĭ papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Nikolaevich Krupenskiĭ papers
1918-1935
36001
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes (3.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, lists, extracts, summaries, reports, appeals, projects, protocols, press analyses, maps, forms, notes, drafts, clippings, newspaper issues, journals, bulletins, and pamphlets relating to the Bessarabian question; relations between Russia, Romania and Bessarabia; the occupation and annexation of Bessarabia by Romania, 1918; and to the Paris Peace Conference.
Krupenskiĭ, Aleksandr Nikolaevich, 1861-1939.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1936.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1912 Published A Brief Sketch of the Bessarabian Gentry, 1812-1912
1914-1918 Chief of the Red Cross in South Russia
pre-1918 Marshal of the Bessarabian nobility and President of the Bessarabian Provincial Zemstvo
1918 November 11 Empowered by the Ukrainian authorities in Odessa to negotiate with the Rumanian authorities and with French, British, and American representatives at Jassy regarding the supplying of Odessa with food
1918 Named representative to the Paris Peace Conference by the Bessarabian Provincial Zemstvo Administration
1919 January 16 Named representative to the Paris Peace Conference by the Committee to Save Bessarabia
1919-1920 Delegate, Paris Peace Conference
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, lists, extracts, summaries, reports, appeals, projects, protocols, press analyses, maps, forms, notes, drafts, clippings, newspaper issues, journals, bulletins, and pamphlets relating to the Bessarabian question; relations between Russia, Romania and Bessarabia; the occupation and annexation of Bessarabia by Romania, 1918; and to the Paris Peace Conference.
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); World War, 1914-1918--Territorial questions--Bessarabia (Moldova and Ukraine); Bessarabia (Moldova and Ukraine)--History.; Romania--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Romania.
- Correspondence, 1918-1935 (Box 1)
  - General (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Adamovich (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Akimov, A. (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Baranovskii, N. (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Barlagean (Barladian, Baraladean), Alexis G. (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Bernshtein, Iakov (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Bilinskaia, N. (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Bonnin, Ayme (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Bourgeois, Leon (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Brianchaninov, A. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Britain, Great, Paris Embassy (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Brohee, Dr. George (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Chappedelaine, S. De (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Le Cri de la Bourse (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Druault, S. (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Epovskii, V. (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Fel'kner, Vladimir (Felkner, Wladimir) (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - France, Government
    - Consulate General, London (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Russian Affairs Section (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Gaillard, Vicomte de (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Gvozdinskaia, I. (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Hotman de Villiers, Dr. P. de (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Hunt, Bampton (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Institut Intermediare International (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Istrati, General I. G. (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Kazimir, V. (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - La Chesnais, P. S. (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Lailler [first name unknown] (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Langue, Lieutenant A. (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - League of Nations Council, President (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Le Bail, P. (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Ligue Francaise Pour la Defense de Droits de l'Homme et du Citoyen (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Monleon, J. (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Nabokov, Konstantin (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Novskii, V. (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Paris Peace Conference
    - President (Box-folder 1: 37)
    - Secretariat General (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Perskii, S. (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Le Progres Civique (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Raffalovich, Arthur (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Reilly, Sidney G. (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Revue des Deux Mondes (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - La Revue de Paris (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - Revue Parlementaire (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Russian Imperial Embassy, Paris (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - Russian Imperial Embassy, Rome (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - Sablin, E. (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - Sazonov, Sergei D. (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - Schilling, M. (Box-folder 1: 50)
  - Schmidt, Alexandre Ch. (Shmidt, Aleksandr K.) (Box-folder 1: 51)
  - Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, Kingdom of, Paris Peace Delegation (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - Shabad, Mikhail (Chabade, Michel) (Box-folder 1: 53)
  - Shtrandtmann, V. N. (Box-folder 1: 54)
  - Simais, Ernest M. (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - Sinadino, Panteleimon V. (Synadino, Pantaleon) (Box-folder 1: 56)
  - St. Leon, E. Martin (Box-folder 1: 57)
  - Le Temps (Box-folder 1: 58)
  - Tverdokhlebov, V. N. (Box-folder 1: 59)
  - Tziganko (Tsyganko), Vladimir (Box-folder 1: 60)
  - "Union" (Russian Telegraph Agency) (Box-folder 1: 61)
  - Union Franco-Russe (Box-folder 1: 62)
  - Vie, Lieutenant Pierre (Box-folder 1: 63)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (Box-folder 1: 64)
- Subject File, 1918-1934 (Boxes 1-3)
  - Agrarian reform in Bessarabia (Box-folder 1: 65)
  - Agrarian reform in Poland (Box-folder 1: 66)
  - Agriculture in Bessarabia, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 67)
  - Armed forces in South Russia, volunteer army (Box-folder 1: 68)
  - Banat of Temesvar, annexation to Rumania (Box-folder 1: 69)
  - Bessarabian Association for the League of Nations (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Bessarabian Commission at Paris Peace Conference (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Bessarabian government, justice (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Bessarabian question (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Brest-Litovsk, Moldavian Peace Delegation at (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Bulgarians in Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Church, Orthodox (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Civil War, cadets (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Collaborators with police, Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Committee to Save Bessarabia, Odessa (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Constitution of Autonomous Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Cooperatives (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Education (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Elections in Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Forests, Bessarabian (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - George, Lloyd (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - History of Bessarabia (resume) (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Inculetz, Ion (Inkulets, Ivan K.) (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - International law (annexation, Plebiscites, etc.) (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Izmail (Ismail), Rumanian occupation of (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Jews, names of (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Judicial affairs in Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Khalippa (Halippa), Panteleimon (Pantaleon) N. (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Kishinev Municipal Club Incident, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Krupenskiĭ, A. N. (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Landowners, Bessarabian (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Maklakoff, Basil (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Marie, Queen Consort of Rumania (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Moldavia, Republic of
    - Council of General Directors (Box-folder 2: 29)
    - Declaration of Independence (Box-folder 2: 30)
    - Establishment of (Box-folder 2: 31)
    - Union with Rumania (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Moldavian Military Congress, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Occupation of Bessarabia, Rumanian
    - General (Box-folder 2: 34)
    - Atrocities (Box-folder 2: 35)
    - Citizenship (Box-folder 2: 36)
    - Conscription (Box-folder 2: 37)
    - Elections (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Orgeev (Orhei), District Council (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Paris Peace Conference (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Political situation in Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Population and nationalities, Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Press
    - French (Box-folder 2: 43)
    - Rumanian, 1919 November (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - Red Cross (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - Refugees, Russian (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - Rumania
    - History (resume) (Box-folder 2: 47)
    - Jews and students (Box-folder 2: 48)
    - Occupation by Germany, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 49)
    - Relations with Bessarabia (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - Russia, relations with Rumania (Box-folder 2: 51)
  - Russian Imperial Embassy, Paris, documents on Bessarabia from (Box-folder 2: 52)
  - Russian Political Conference, Paris (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Sanitary conditions in Serbia, Rumania, and Bessarabia (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Schools, nationalization of, etc. (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Sfatul Tarei
    - General (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Organization (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Political orientation (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Relations with City Councils (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Representatives' rejection of Resolutions (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Soroki (Soroca), District Council (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Stroesco, Basil (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Treaties, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Tziganko (Tsyganko), Vladimir (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Ukrainians arrived in Bucharest, 1919 December 25 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Union of Bessarabia with Rumania, Acts of (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Unions, Bessarabian (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - United States of America, address of President, 1917 January 22 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Zemstvos (Box-folder 3: 17)
- Speeches and Writings, 1919 (Box 3)
  - "A Propos de la Bessarabie," published article, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - "Avant Propos," copy of typewritten foreward, 1919 December 28 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - "The Bessarabian 'Parliament' (Sfatul Tzerii)," copy of typewritten article, undated (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - "General Program of the Representatives of the Bessarabian Population," handwritten manuscript, 1919 December 10 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Letter to the Editor of L'Italie, handwritten draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Letter to the Editor of L'Oeuvre, handwritten draft, 1919 December 28 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Notes for articles, handwritten, undated (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Notes for speech, untitled, handwritten manuscript, London, 1919 July (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Untitled article on Bessarabian question, handwritten draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Untitled article on Bessarabian question, copy of typewritten manuscript, 1919 August (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Untitled article in Pravda, interview with Theodore Emandi, handwritten draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 28)
- Printed Matter, 1914-1920 (Boxes 3-6)
  - Clippings, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Journal and bulletins
    - Bulletin d'Informations Roumaines, No. 9, 10, 12, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Current History, No. 3, annotated, 1920 March (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - L'Europe Nouvelle, No. 8, annotated, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - L'Image de la Bessarabie, No. 225-227, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Kishinevskiia Eparkhial'nyia Vedomosti, No. 16-17, 21-22, 1914 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Les Peuples Libres, No. 6 (2 copies), No. 7, annotated, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Le Progres Civique, No. 13-15, 17, 20, annotated, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Revue Parlementaire, No. 39-42, annotated, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Russkii Kur'er, No. 36, 40, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - La Transylvanie, No. 20-22, 1919 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Newspaper issues
    - Actiunea Romana, 1 issue (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - Adeverul, 1 issue, annotated (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Basarabia, 2 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Bessarabia, 5 issues, 3 annotated (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Bessarabskaia Zhyzn', 4 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Christian Science Monitor, 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Les Dernieres Nouvelles De Middi, 2 issues (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Epoca, 2 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - La France Libre, 2 issues (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - La Gazette de Lausanne, 8 issues, 5 annotated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - L'Humanite, 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - L'Impartial Suisse, 7 issues, annotated (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Le Journal des Debats, 1 issue, annotated (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - La Lanterne, 2 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Le Matin, 2 issues, annotated (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - The Morning Post, 3 issues (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - Nashe Slovo, 3 issues, annotated (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Odesskii Listok, 2 issues, annotated (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - L'Oeuvre, 1 issue, annotated (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Prikarpatskaia Rus', 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - La Republique Russe, 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Rossiia, 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Sfatul Tarii, 2 issues, annotated (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - Sfatul Tserii, 5 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - La Suisse, 1 issue (Box-folder 5: 20)
    - Svobodnaia Mysl', 4 issues (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Il Tempo, 3 issues (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Le Temps, 5 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - La Tribune de Geneve, 5 issues, 1 annotated (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Vechernii Biulleten', 1 issue (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - Viitorul, 2 issues, annotated (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Pamphlets
    - D. Draghicesco, La Besarabie et la Droit des Peuples, Paris, annotated, 1918 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - N. Iogra, Des Roumains dans la Dobrogea, Jassy, annotated, 1917 (Box-folder 6: 8)
- Miscellany, 1919-1921 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Notes
  - Handbill
  - Open letter
  - Form
  - Lists of documents, guests, and recipients of informative material
- Clippings, 1919-1921 (Boxes 7-9)
  Scope and Contents note
  Three bound volumes, and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - 1919 March-August (Box 7)
  - 1919 August - 1920 January (Box 8)
  - 1920 January - 1921 January (Box 9)